773-484-8309 susan.nelson.editor@gmail.com

### **SUMMARY**

Award-winning reporter/writer/editor/manager of online, print, and verbal communications. Precise, versatile, deadline-trained team player who creates engaging, convincing original copy on nearly any topic, from squibs to in-depth reports; accurately recasts complex ideas and information into clear English; and enhances the effectiveness of others' writings.

Experienced in journalism, education, grant writing, Web sites and blogs, publishing, government, research, science, and the arts. Positions held range from reporter for the *Chicago Tribune* to editor/manager of magazines, and from public information to educational publishing and classroom instruction.

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

### FREELANCE WRITER/EDITOR, Chicago, IL Currently; 1976 to 1998

Research, write, and edit a wide variety of articles and special products

- **Lincoln Park Village**—co-edit monthly newsletter; edit all print and online materials.
- Commercial clients—develop, write, revise marketing copy for Web sites and blogs.
- **Not-for-profit clients—**write and edit grant proposals, Web sites, blogs, appeals.
- Field Museum of Natural History—researched and wrote articles and guidebooks.
- The Washington Post—Chicago stringer (reporter) for national desk.
- **Chicago Sun-Times**—wrote on-the-scene reports on the 1976 Guatemalan earthquakes with death toll of 23,000.
- **Chicago Reader**—researched and wrote weekly Neighborhood News columns about local politics and urban problems.
- **Encyclopaedia Britannica, World Book, and Compton's** encyclopedias—researched and wrote biographies, obituaries, special reports.
- **Reader's Digest**—produced report on battered women.
- **Esquire**—numerous writing assignments on Chicago topics.
- **PBS**—Chicago stringer for "Inside Edition," Hodding Carter's TV show on the media.
- The Nature Conservancy—researched/wrote/edited monthly newsletter
- **Shedd Aquarium**—researched and wrote for annual report.
- Henry Regnery/Contemporary Books—edited a dozen manuscripts into books.

### PEARSON EDUCATION/SCOTT FORESMAN, Glenview, IL 2005 to 2010

Leading national publisher of print and online publications

### **Editor, Reading Department**

- During five-year tenure earned increasing editorial and management responsibilities in editing online, audio, and print products.
- The sole editor of a national student book (Grade 6), whose writing on a tornadodestroyed Kansas town's comeback merited a byline and author's photograph.

### CHICAGO PUBLIC SCHOOLS, Chicago, IL 1998 to 2005 Classroom Teacher

Taught Grades 1 to 7, from reading to science, in three inner-city Chicago schools.

#### STAFF WRITING AND EDITING EXPERIENCE

# MACLEAN HUNTER PUBLISHING COMPANY, Chicago, IL Editor, Remodeling Contractor

Revamped and rebranded monthly 30,000-circulation trade magazine for remodelers/architects, hired and supervised staff of five, coordinated editorial board.

Susan Nelson Page 2

## UNITED STATES ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY, Chicago, IL Senior Level Writer/Editor

Originated national public-information program for Great Lakes cleanup, planned and held public meetings, produced brochures and wrote speeches, initiated and maintained media contacts, and edited 40,000-circulation monthly magazine for six-state Region V Midwestern office.

# CHICAGO TRIBUNE MAGAZINE, Chicago, IL Articles Editor/Writer

First woman staff member, when *Tribune's* Sunday circulation was nearly one million, to produce special-theme issues for weekly magazine, coordinate arts coverage, assign/edit articles from a stable of free-lance writers, and write monthly in-depth articles and profiles.

## CHICAGO TRIBUNE, Chicago, IL Reporter/Writer

Progressed from assistant fashion editor to entertainment writer, consumer-affairs columnist, general-assignment feature reporter, writer of "off-beat" columns and interviews, and copy editor before advancing to *Magazine* position.

### **ADJUNCT INSTRUCTOR**

Truman College, English as a Second Language, GED (1992 – 1998)

Urban Gateways, Writing Residencies, Inner-City Public/Private Schools (1988 – 1998)

Columbia College, Journalism, Writing (1976 – 1985)

Stanford University, Magazine Writing (1975)

#### OTHER EXPERIENCE

UNITED STATES CENSUS BUREAU, Chicago, IL 4/2010 to 8/2010 Crew Leader – Trained and supervised staff of 18 enumerators in 2010 Census.

### **AWARDS**

- Knight/NEH Journalism Fellowship to Stanford University, 1975. Independent study of ethics in journalism and in the United States; fact-seeking travel with other Fellows.
- The Associated Press 1st-place writing award for in-depth feature article on religion in Chicago.
- U.S. Environmental Protection Agency special award for management of contracts that saved the government \$325,000 in one year.

### **EDUCATION**

**DePauw University**, B.A. in English Literature; Minors in History, Psychology, Education, French

**DePaul University,** Post-Graduate Courses in Education

### **PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS**

Chicago Journalists Association, Secretary and Board Member Chicago Women in Publishing, Member Association of Women Journalists, Member